Guide to the Altrusa International Inc., Club of Houston Records
University of Houston Libraries
Altrusa International Inc., Club of Houston Records
1936-
1999-2009
02/2009-004
Altrusa International Club of Houston
5.50 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The collection is organized in 17 series and is housed in 6 boxes that document the organization and community volunteer programs of the Altrusa Club of Houston. The collection includes meeting minutes, financial records, and annual records. Concerning the club's yearly activities, there are newsletters from 1956-2008 and yearbooks ranging from 1936-2008.
Historical Note:
Altrusa International Inc., Club of Houston was organized in 1925, as part of Altrusa International which was founded in 1917, in Nashville, Tennessee. The Altrusa motto, “Patriotism, Efficiency, Service”, reflects their dedication to community involvement and volunteerism. The Club of Houston has established several community volunteer programs, including the Friends and Neighbors Project (FAN), Make a Difference Day, and Hearts-Hands for Service Foundation. The FAN Project encompasses Story time Saturdays, a Summer Reading Program, and Holiday Gifts for seniors. Altrusa works with Literary Advance of Houston, in connection with the FAN Project. Make a Difference Day is held every October, with the Galveston Bay Foundation. Hearts-Hands for Service, founded in 1983, assists women, children, and seniors in the Houston area. Members of the Club of Houston also participate in a mentoring program for the ASTRA Club. The Houston Club awards scholarships and grants to local students.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Altrusa International Club of Houston
Genre/Form of Material:
Bylaws (administrative records); Correspondence; Ephemera; Minutes; Newsletters; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Yearbooks
Topical Term:
Nonprofit organizations -- Texas -- Houston; Voluntarism; Women -- Societies and clubs -- Texas -- Houston
Accruals:
Additional materials were acquired in 2012.
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
The collection is organized in 17 series and is housed in 6 boxes that document the organization and community volunteer programs of the Altrusa Club of Houston. The collection includes meeting minutes, financial records, and annual records. Concerning the club's yearly activities, there are newsletters from 1956-2008 and yearbooks ranging from 1936-2008. The collection contains information regarding community volunteer programs, as well as photographs from several events. There are four scrapbooks in this collection, as well as artifacts.
Detailed List of Contents
- History, id72057
  - 70th Anniversary’s History Decades, id72091 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographies of Presidents, 1930-1934, 1957-1959, 1965-1967; id72092 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - “History of District Nine”, 1973; id72093 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Oral History Project, 2002; id72094 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Pamphlets, id72095 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Bylaws and Policies, id72058
  - 1995, 2000, id72096 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 2005-2007, 2007-2009, id72097 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Organization Meeting Minutes, Correspondence and Financial Records, id72059
  - July 1951- June 1955, id72098 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - July 1955- June 1959, id72099 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - July 1959- June 1963, id72100 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - July 1969- June 1972, id72101 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - July 1972- June 1975, id72102 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - July 1975- June 1980, id72103 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - July 1980- June 1986, id72104 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - July 1986- June 1992, id72105 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - April 1993-September 1993, id133175 (Box 1, Folder 15a)
  - June 1994- May 1997, id72106 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - June 1997-May 1998, id133176 (Box 1, Folder 16a)
  - June 1998- May 2001, id72107 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - June 2001- May 2002, id72108 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - June 2002- May 2005, id72109 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - June 2005- May 2008, id72110 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Annual Reports and Miscellaneous Information, id72060
  - 1991-1995, id72111 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1996-2001, id72112 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 2001-2008, id72113 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Member Activities, Information and Resources, id72061
  - Altrusa International, Inc Encyclopedia, 1997; id72114 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Induction Ceremonies, id72115 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Member Accents: Acknowledgements of member activities and achievements, id72116 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Membership Lists and General Information, 1994-2008; id72117 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - New Member Orientations, 2000-2008; id72118 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - New Membership Recruitment and Mentoring, id72119 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Articles, 1960, 1993, 1995, 2005; id72120 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Secretaries Workshop: “Building a Solid Foundation”, 1993; id133177 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Secretaries Workshop: “The Nuts and Bolts of Building Altrusa”, 1994; id133178 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Leadership Training: “Leaders in Service”, 1999; id133179 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Various, undated; id133180 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- In Memoriam, id72062
  - Margaret Dudley Jones, 1902-1998; id72121 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Lavelle Yarbrough, 1919-2001; id72122 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Renilda E. Hilkemeyer, 1915-2006; id72123 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Organizations and Projects, id72063
  - Friends and Neighbors (FAN) Project, id72124 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Friends and Neighbors (FAN), Burbank Elementary, 1994-1997; id72125 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Friends and Neighbors (FAN), Burbank Elementary Photographs, id72126 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Friends and Neighbors (FAN), Dawning Year’s Academy, 1998; id72127 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Friends and Neighbors (FAN), Story Time, id72128 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Furr High School, Protecting Your Wealth, 2003; id72129 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - ASTRA Club, 2006-2007; id72130 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Scholarship and Grant Awards, id72064
  - Houston Altrusa Fund, id72131 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Grants Awarded, 1999-2000; id72132 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Scholarships Awarded, 2008-2009; id72133 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Award Nominations, id72065
  - 1988, 1990-1991, 1993-1996, id72134 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1996-1998, id72135 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 1998-2002, 2005-2006, id72136 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 2006-2009, id72137 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Certificates, 1994-2009; id72138 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Conferences and Conventions, id72066
  - Altrusa International, Inc First Annual Conference, 1956; id72139 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Altrusa International, Inc Convention, 1957; id72140 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Altrusa International, Inc Second Annual Conference, 1957; id72141 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Altrusa International, Inc Third Annual Conference, 1958; id72142 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Altrusa International, Inc International Convention, 1989; id72143 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Altrusa International, Inc 45th Annual Conference, 2001; id72144 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Altrusa International, Inc District Conference, 2006; id72145 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Altrusa International Foundation, Inc Dallas International Convention, 2001, 2007; id72146 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Photographs, id72147 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- The Federation of Houston Professional Women Awards Banquets, id72067
  - 1990-2001, id72148 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Newsletters, id72068
  - Gov-O-Gram, 1956-1958; id72149 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - The Scratch Pad, 1956-1959; id72150 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - The Scratch Pad, 1969-1971; id72151 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - The Scratch Pad, 1972-1973, 1988-1991; id72152 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Service Bulletin, 1970-1971; id72153 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - News of the Mighty 9th, 1970-1972; id72154 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Altrusa Today!, 1991-1994; id72155 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Houston Highlights, 1994-1996; id72156 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Houston Highlights, 1997-1998; id72157 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Houston Highlights, 1999-2000; id72158 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Houston Highlights, 2001-2002; id72159 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Houston Highlights, 2003-2004; id72160 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Houston Highlights, 2005-2006; id72161 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Houston Highlights, 2007-2008; id72162 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Houston Highlights CD, 1994-2001; id72163 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - International Altrusian: Biennium Program Issue, April 1993; id133181 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Yearbooks, id72069
  - 1936-1950, id72164 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1950-1960, 1964-1965, 1969-1970, id72289 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1970-1980, id72290 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1980-1985, 1988-1991, id72291 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1992-1995, id72292 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1995-1999, id72293 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1999-2003, 2005-2006, id72294 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 2006-2008, id72295 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Yearbook Judging Criteria and Score Sheets, id72296 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Photographs, id72070
  - Altrusa Women in Oklahoma (1950s), id72297 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Golden Hobby House, 1977, 2002, 2003, 2007; id72298 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Fundraisers, 1997, 2000, 2007, 2008; id72299 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Make a Difference Day, 1999; id72300 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Cullen Middle School, 2007; id72301 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Hats Off to Literacy, 2007; id72302 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Building Strong Libraries, Lockhart Elementary, 2008; id72303 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Picture CDs, 2004-2009; id72304 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Oversized Altrusa Convention Photograph, 1935; id72305 (File cabinet F, Drawer 9, Ovs item 1)
- Cookbook, id72071
  - Altrusa International Cookbook, 1991; id72306 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Artifacts, id72073
  - Altrusa Service Pin, id72311 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Altrusa International, Inc., Plaque, id72312 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Altrusa Friends and Neighbors Shirt, id72313 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Blue Ribbons, id72314 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Governor’s Pin, Etta Jane Butler, 1969; id72315 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Altrusa International 50th Anniversary Keychain, 1917-1967; id72316 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Distinguished Service Award, Etta Jane Butler, 1969; id72317 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Altrusan of the Year, Etta Jane Butler, 1970-1971; id72318 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Vocational Nursing Program Support Award (box), 2004; id72319 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - ASTRA Mentoring Program Award, 2007; id72320 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Recognition Pin, 52nd Annual District Conference, 2008; id72321 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Scrapbooks, id72072
  - Altrusa Club of Houston, 1925-1990; id72307 (Ovs box 5, Ovs item 1)
  - Altrusa Club of Houston, 1940-1959; id72308 (Ovs box 5, Ovs item 2)
  - Altrusa International Inc., of Houston, 1992-1994; id72309 (Ovs box 5, Ovs item 3)
  - Altrusa International Inc., of Houston, 2007-2008; id72310 (Ovs box 5, Ovs item 4)